W. Somerset Maugham Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
W. Somerset Maugham Papers 1897-1966 (bulk 1897-1946)
MSS47852
Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965
22 items
7 containers
2 linear feet
4 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author. Correspondence, manuscripts, a speech, a bibliography, news clippings, press releases, and a program.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965.; Maugham, W. Somerset (William Somerset), 1874-1965. Of human bondage. 1915.
Subjects
English literature.
Titles
William Somerset Maugham papers
Occupations
Authors.
Provenance
The papers of W. Somerset Maugham, author, were given to the Library of Congress by Maugham in 1946, with additional material received by gift, transfer, and purchase from Maugham and others between 1950 and 1995.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on four reels for use in the Manuscript Division Reading Room and under the same conditions applying to use of the original manuscripts. The film cannot be lent or reproduced.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of W. Somerset Maugham (1874-1965) span the years 1897-1966 with the bulk of material dating from 1897 to 1946. The collection consists of a bibliography, correspondence, newspaper clippings, press releases, a program, a speech, and writings. The writings include the manuscript of Maugham's autobiographical novel, Of Human Bondage, and its earlier, unpublished version, "The Artistic Temperament of Stephen Carey." Featured in the correspondence is a letter Maugham wrote to Martha V. Maremont concerning the origin of the title and the development of various characters in Of Human Bondage. There is considerable publicity material in the papers documenting Maugham's presentation of the manuscript to the Library of Congress in 1946.
Also included are installments of the play, For Services Rendered, published in the London Sunday Times in 1932.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Bibliography, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1934, 1941, 1966, undated (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings, 1932 (Box 1)
- Press releases, 1946 (Box 1)
- Program, 1946 (Box 1)
- Writings (Box 2, Reel 1)
  Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 12,920
  - "The Artistic Temperament of Stephen Carey," 1897-1898 (Box 2, Reel 1)
    - Vol. 1 (Box 2, Reel 1)
    - Vol. 2 (Box 2, Reel 2)
    - Loose material (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Of Human Bondage (Box 3, Reel 3)
    - Foreword, 1936, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Draft, 1911-1914 (Box 4, Reel 3)
      - Vols. 1-4 (Box 4, Reel 3)
      - Vols. 5-8 (Box 5, Reel 3)
      - Vols. 9-12 (Box 6, Reel 4)
      - Vols. 13-16 (Box 7, Reel 4)